Quantum computing is entered the era of utility
量子コンピューティングは実用の時代に突入しました
meaning that we can begin to use quantum computers to solve
つまり、量子コンピューターを使って問題を解き始めることが
real world problems including some that are very difficult
できるようになったということです。中には古典コンピューターには
for classical computers
非常に難しい問題も含まれています
a common theme in the current era
現在の時代に共通するテーマとして
is that a problem is solved
ある問題が初めて
for the first time on a quantum computer
量子コンピューターで解かれ
and then subsequently people find a way to do it on a classical
その後、古典コンピューターでも解く方法が見つかる
computer this cycle of classical
というサイクルがあります。この古典コンピューティングと
and quantum computing pushing each other to their
量子コンピューティングがお互いの限界を
limits will likely continue
押し広げるサイクルは、おそらく続くでしょう
for a few years there are classes of problems where quantum
しばらくの間は、量子コンピューティングが
computing can have approvable advantage
証明可能な優位性を持つ問題のクラスがあります
over classical computing
古典コンピューティングに対して
given progress in areas such
エラーの削減などの分野での進展や
as reduction of errors and the number of cubits available
利用可能なqubitの数が増えれば、その優位性は高まります
there are also entire application areas
また、アプリケーション領域全体として
where quantum computing
量子コンピューティングが
might be useful in the relatively near term
比較的近い将来に役立つ可能性のある分野もあります
one of these areas is quanta machine learning or qml
そのような分野の一つが、量子機械学習（QML）です
quanta machine learning refers to
量子機械学習とは
the application of quantity computing to any type of machine
量子コンピューティングをあらゆる種類の機械
learning process there are of course
学習プロセスに応用することです。もちろん
many types of machine learning
機械学習には多くの種類があります
two types of particular interest or
特に注目すべき2つのタイプは
supervised learning in which you
教師あり学習と教師なし学習です。教師あり学習では
train in algorithm using a labeled dataset
ラベル付きデータセットを使ってアルゴリズムを訓練します
and unsupervised learning in which
教師なし学習では
the algorithm works from unlabeled samples
アルゴリズムがラベルなしのサンプルから学習し
and attempts to learn about the distribution
その分布について理解しようとします
or the function that generates it
またはそれを生成する関数について
an unsupervised algorithm might
教師なしアルゴリズムは例えば
for example learn how to generate new samples
同じ分布から新しいサンプルを生成する方法を学んだり
from the same distribution or how to
または似たような特性を持つグループに
cluster the samples into groups with similar characteristics
サンプルをクラスタリングする方法を学んだりします
both supervised and unsupervised learning often involved
教師ありと教師なし学習のどちらも、多くの場合
the embedding of data in higher dimensional spaces
データをより高次元の空間に埋め込む処理が含まれます
and manipulation of data in higher dimensional spaces
そして高次元空間でのデータ操作というと
should make us think of quantum computing
量子コンピューティングを思い浮かべるはずです
let me explain imagine trying to solve the problem of whether
その理由を説明しましょう。平面上のデータ点が
to classify a data point from the plane
丸か×かを分類するという問題を
as a circle or a cross given the labeled training data here
解くことを考えてみてください。ここにはラベル付きの訓練データがあります
sometimes data can be clearly separated by a line
データが直線でくっきり分けられる場合もあります
or plane in low dimensions
低次元での平面など
as shown here and classifying these data points according
このように示されており、直線の上下でデータ点を分類するのは
to those above the line
線より上のデータ点と
and below the line should be
線より下のデータ点を分けるのは
no problem but look at this distribution
問題ないはずです。でも、この分布を見てください
clearly there's no visible line that separates the data points
データ点を分けられる直線が明らかに見当たりません
however for this data we could imagine some
しかし、このデータに対しては何らかの
mapping from two dimensions to three dimensions
2次元から3次元へのマッピングが考えられます
such that after applying the mapping our data looks
そのマッピングを適用した後、データは
like this and there's clearly a plane which separates the two
このようになり、2つのクラスを分ける平面が明確に存在します
classes in which we can use
その平面を分類に
for classification if this treatment seems a bit simplistic
利用できます。この説明が少し単純すぎると感じたなら
you're right we can't just put the data points we want
その通りです。データ点を単に
further up with no justification
理由なく上方向に移動させることはできません
there has to be a mapping
マッピングが必要です
from the two d distribution that effectively separates
2次元の分布から、データ点を
our data points so we can
効果的に分離するマッピングが必要です。そうして
use the mapping to classify new data points
そのマッピングを使って新しいデータ点を分類します
this will be discussed more in the lesson giving a machine
これについては、機械学習の復習を行うレッスンで
learning recap but suffice it to say
詳しく説明しますが、要点を言えば
that the problem can be viewed
この問題は
as trying many different mappings into this higher dimensional
この高次元空間への様々なマッピングを試して
space to see which mappings yield the best
どのマッピングが異なるクラスの
separation of data points of different classes
データ点を最もよく分離するかを見つける問題として見ることができます
this manipulation of data in higher dimensions
この高次元でのデータ操作は
is one area where quantum computing
量子コンピューティングが
may have a big impact to understand why
大きな影響を与えられる分野の一つです。その理由を理解するために
let's return to the differences between classical
古典コンピューティングと
and quantum computing just
量子コンピューティングの違いに戻りましょう。
as classical computers use bits of information
古典コンピューターが情報のビットを使うように
quantum computers use cubits
量子コンピューターはqubitを使います
but for a given number of bits say four
しかし、ある一定のビット数、例えば4ビットの場合
a classical computer can take on any of the
古典コンピューターは
two to the four or sixteen possible states
2の4乗、つまり16通りの可能な状態のいずれかを取れます
a quantum computer can also access sixteen possible states
量子コンピューターも同様に16通りの状態にアクセスできますが
but it can exist in a super position of all
すべての16の状態の重ね合わせとして
sixteen states simultaneously
同時に存在することができます
and operations can be performed on this entire superposition
そして、その重ね合わせ全体に対して演算を実行できます
for four cubits this may not seem
4つのqubitではそれほど大きなことに
like such a big deal but imagine what could be done with
思えないかもしれませんが、2の20乗、あるいは
a quantum computer in two to the twenty or
量子コンピューターで2の20乗または
two to the one hundred and twenty seven
2の127乗で何ができるかを想像してみてください
states simultaneously there are many other differences
これらの状態を同時に扱えます。古典コンピューティングと
between classical and quantity computing that will
量子コンピューティングの間には他にも多くの違いがあり
all play a role in this subject
それらすべてがこの分野で重要な役割を果たします
quantum states have complex probability amplitudes
量子状態は複素確率振幅を持ちます
manipulations of quantum systems are carried out with
量子システムの操作はユニタリ演算子で行われ
unitary operators and quantum computers are subject to different
量子コンピューターは古典コンピューターとは異なる種類の
kinds of noise than classical computers
ノイズの影響を受けます
these differences will come up
これらの違いは
throughout your quantity machine learning work in areas
量子機械学習の研究の中で、データエンコーディング、
like data encoding feature mapping in error mitigation
特徴マッピング、エラー緩和といった分野で登場してきます
in some cases these differences between classical
場合によっては、古典コンピューターと
and quantum computers allow us to design entirely
量子コンピューターのこれらの違いにより、まったく
new algorithms now that was a very brief overview
新しいアルゴリズムを設計できるようになります。以上は
to the union of two immensely complicated fields
非常に複雑な2つの分野の融合についての
but hopefully two things are clear
簡単な概観でした。しかし、少なくとも2点は
machine learning often solves problems
明確になったはずです。機械学習はしばしば
by manipulating data in very high dimensions
非常に高い次元でデータを操作することで問題を解きます
and second quantum computers are well suited
そして第二に、量子コンピューターは
to manipulating data in high dimensions
高次元でのデータ操作に適しており
and do so differently than classical systems
古典システムとは異なる方法でそれを行います
this should give you a sense
これで、なぜ機械学習が
for why machine learning is a promising field
有望な分野であるかがわかるでしょう
for the application of useful quantum computing
量子コンピューティングの実用的な応用として